Soumen Basu

Email: mail.basu.s@gmail.com
Web: https://www.cse.iitd.ac.in/~soumen
Phone: +91 9051501506
LinkedIn: www.linkedin.com/in/basusoumen

Profile Summary

PhD in Computer Vision, Machine Learning / Deep Learning. Master's in Computer Science with 3+ years of industry and 5+ years of academic research experience. Looking for Research Scientist/ Leadership positions in cutting edge CV/ ML initiatives.

Education

PhD in Computer Science

Indian Institute of Technology Delhi (07/2019 – 01/2024)

- Area: Computer Vision, Deep Learning
- Thesis: Deep Learning-based Gallbladder Cancer Detection from Ultrasound
- Received the highly prestigious Prime Minister's Research Fellowship (awarded to 3.5% of PhD students from top-10 national institutes in India)
- Pioneered the first AI-based Gallbladder Cancer (GBC) detection model from Ultrasound (US), published at CVPR 2022.
- Innovated accurate, efficient, and explainable models for GBC detection potential to improve the 5-year survival rate from 5% to 57% with AI-based early detection.
- Published in high-impact international venues like CVPR, MICCAI, Medical Image Analysis, and Lancet Regional Health.
- Engineered a cloud application prototype and deployed models on an IoT device (Jetson) for real-time clinical testing in multiple hospitals across India.
- Teaching Assistant for Computer Vision, ML, Data Structure courses. Recognized with the Outstanding Teaching Assistant Award for the Machine Learning course.

M. Tech in Computer Science (equivalent to an MS)

Indian Institute of Technology Delhi (07/2013 – 06/2015)

- Achieved All India Rank 99 out of 224,160 candidates in GATE 2013 (Computer Science)
- Thesis: Randomized Rounding using Random Walks An Experimental Study

Areas of Interest

- Computer Vision, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Medical Image Analysis, Image or Video Processing,
- Un-supervised/ Weakly-supervised/ Self-supervised Learning, Contrastive Learning, Explainable AI
- Transformers, CNN, Foundation Models

Technical Skills

- Python, PyTorch, OpenCV, Scikit-Learn, Numpy, Pandas
- CUDA, SQL, AWS, Git

Publications

- 1. **S. Basu**, M. Gupta, P. Rana, P. Gupta, C. Arora. "Surpassing the Human Accuracy: Detecting Gallbladder Cancer from USG with Curriculum Learning", CVPR 2022.
- 2. **S. Basu**, S. Singla, M. Gupta, P. Rana, P. Gupta, C. Arora. "Unsupervised Contrastive Learning of Image Representations from Ultrasound Videos with Hard Negative Mining", MICCAI 2022.
- 3. **S. Basu**, M. Gupta, P. Rana, P. Gupta, C. Arora. "RadFormer: Transformers with global-local attention for interpretable and accurate Gallbladder Cancer detection", Elsevier Medical Image Analysis (IF: 13.828) 2023.
- 4. S. Basu, A. Papanai, M. Gupta, P. Gupta, C. Arora. "Gall Bladder Cancer Detection from US Images with Only Image Level Labels", MICCAI 2023
- 5. M. Gupta, **S. Basu**, C. Arora. "How reliable are the metrics used for assessing reliability in medical imaging?", MICCAI 2023 (Oral Paner)
- 6. P. Gupta, **S. Basu**, et al. "Deep-learning enabled ultrasound based accurate detection of gallbladder cancer: A prospective diagnostic study", The LANCET Regional Health South East Asia 2023.
- 7. P. Gupta, **S. Basu**, et al. "Deep learning models for differentiation of xanthogranulomatous cholecystitis and gallbladder cancer on ultrasound", Indian Journal of Gastroenterology (Accepted).

Professional Experience

Applied Scientist Intern

Amazon Inc. (07/2023 – Present)

- Area: Computer Vision, Machine Learning
- Developed an ML model for detecting stray objects in conveyor belts, optimizing production.
- Saved \$120,000/ year in license costs with an in-house model.
- Achieved 21% better precision over the currently deployed model on backtesting.
- Developed a model for predicting breakdowns from machine health data achieved 11% better precision than current model

Research Assistant

Penn State University (08/2018 – 05/2019)

 Designed an optimization framework to reduce operational costs by 18-40% for geographically distributed key-value storage over the public cloud.

Member of Technical Staff

Adobe Systems (07/2015 – 07/2018)

- Developed backend REST APIs for data pipeline on digital ad entities on Terabyte scale.
- Improved the scaling of automatic syncing, and CRUD operations of search engine ad data to production DB.

Leadership Skills

- Mentoring and Collaboration: Mentored 2 Undergrads, 1 Masters student, and 3 RAs to became successful co-authors in CVPR 2022, MICCAI 2022, and MICCAI 2023. Delivered high quality publications in the mentioned venues.
- Management and Leadership: Led a team of 6 Teaching Assistants to manage the Machine Learning course with 150 students. Successfully assigned duties, coordinated tutorial sessions and examinations, and received the Outstanding TA award for exceptional leadership.
- **Teamwork and Organization:** Organized a remote and cross-functional team involving doctors and engineers for doctoral research. Currently working with a team geographically distributed across NA, EU, and APAC at Amazon.
- Resource Management: Managed lab resources for the group containing 17 graduate and 16 undergraduate/ interns, ensuring efficient utilization and an organized environment for the group.
- **Hiring Talent:** Conducted technical interviews for the recruitment of Interns and Research Assistants, facilitating talent assessment and successful on-boarding of candidates.

Grants and Awards

- Prime Minister's Research Fellowship (2021-2023) Award value Stipend: INR 22,00,000 and Travel: INR 5,00,000
- Selection for Oral Presentation at MICCAI 2023 (only 3% of the submitted papers)
- Outstanding Teaching Assistant Award for Machine Learning course (2023)
- MICCAI Student Travel Award (2022) first authors of highest quality papers. Award value: \$1000
- CVPR DEI Travel Grant (2022) award value \$600.
- Winner (2nd) of Object Detection Challenge, ICVGIP 2020

Reviewer Experience

Served as reviewer in Computer Vision/ Machine Learning at AAAI 2023, AAAI 2024, CVPR 2023, CVPR 2024, ICCV 2023, WACV 2024, IEEE Transactions of Medical Imaging (IF: 11.03)

Talks

- Oral Session: Machine Learning II Towards Transparent AI, MICCAI 2023 (Oct 2023)
- SciTech Talks Podcast (Jul 2023)
- RME Data Science India Offsite Event, Amazon Inc (Jul 2023)
- PhD Seminar, Department of Computer Science, IIT Delhi (Nov 2022)

Reference

Available on Request